[Music]
Welcome to new busy central launch
edition 2025 release wave two. Today we
will present new types of documents in
uh e documents framework e- shipments by
but e shipments we think e shipments and
e transfer shipments. My name is
Alexander Toto. I'm product manager
responsor for this functionality and I
have my colleague Maronos. Hi. Hi
everyone, my name is Manus and I am a
engineer in business central.
>> So let's see first what is a shipment?
What does it
um we use this expression but in general
authorities in different countries can
use different expression different names
e shipment or e delivery note or eway
bill maybe some other countries
different expressions as well. So all of
them are actually the same. This is your
shipment in business central in
electronical file. So as I said this is
just digital version. Traditionally we
have all delivery nodes or shipments
whatever we call this. We have this in
the system. We have this in almost all
ERP systems. But now this is digital
version of shipment we already had. This
is required and it can be required
actually in many countries. uh somewhere
this is already mandatory for example in
Mexico in India this is already
mandatory in some other countries it
will be mandatory soon required soon for
example in Serbia and few other
countries it will be this is already uh
announced it will be required soon but
other side we have in European Union uh
introduction of new EFTI regulation for
electronic transport documents now we
can assume and I try to to avoid
assumptions maybe it will be mandatory
maybe it will not but minimum uh this is
something what will allow actually
require from authorities to receive
digital versions of shipment on delivery
nodes. So if it's already exist we will
enable it and if it become mandatory we
will localize.
So um what is new actually in e
documents in this release this is
something what we already had in
outbound e documents in outbound we had
sales invoice sales create memos this is
something what we already had earlier
and with this release we extended it to
sales shipments and transfer shipments
as well
um both of them are available in this
release but it open a door for extending
this because now we have new document
type and we We have probably more and
more document types in the future
depends of uh uh regulatory
requirements. Uh what will be required
and some maybe some other business
reasons. So it opens door for us to
introduce new documents types and for
you if you want to build on top of that
and before we jump into demo I just
wanted to emphasize the most important
business value of this functionality.
First it improve and standardize whole
workflow process. So it support new
document types for structure e
documentation especially in countries
where this is mandatory. So it will be
much easier and standardized. You will
have everything in your framework and
this is ready for localization expansion
for new countries. As I already
mentioned in few countries this is
already mandatory or will be mandatory.
Currently in the system we do not have
some specific uh file uh for specific
localization. This is just example you
can use in demos. But as soon as we
start localization of that, we will
localize basin on specific countries. So
Magnus, it's your time. Thank you. All
right, let's uh let's look at how this
actually looks in the product. So uh
today I will show you how to actually
post a sales shipment and create an
electronic document from that. And
normally when we create uh electronic
invoices, we send them to a a provider
that then forwards them for instance in
the Pebble network. But today I thought
why not do something a little bit
differently. So instead of actually
sending it to a provider, I will uh just
be exporting the the shipment into an eh
shipment and then I will be sending it
via email using our workflow. And I'll
show you all all now how that works. So
I'll go to a customer have set up with a
document sending profile that is set up
to use e documents and workflow. And if
I just go to uh workflow here, then we
can take a quick look at how the
workflow for sending shipments I created
looks.
So in this one, it's uh very much
similar to the standard ones we provide.
I just have the event when any document
is created and then the type is a sales
shipment. Then we send it using the
service I have set up e shipments. And
this one is not connected to any
provider uh or any integration. So it
will just export the shipment and as you
can see in the second line of the
workflow when that has happened and the
e document service status has changed
into exported then we will email uh both
a PDF of the sales shipment but also the
electronic document. So let's see that
work. So I will go create a new sales
order
and I will fill in a reference here ref
4321 and then I'll just go down and fill
out any item for the demo quantity of
one and then we can post this and we
will just ship it.
So if I just scroll to our quantity
shipped here, we can actually quickly
navigate to the posted sales shipment.
And like on sales invoices and sales
credit memos, you can navigate to the e
document by opening the related e
document open here. And here we see that
we do indeed have an e document. It is
also exported.
And I set up my own email on this
customer just for the demonstration
purposes. So in the background, if I
open up my email here, you can see we
just received a email. It is empty. I
didn't put anything into the body, but
you can go do that in report selection.
But I just wanted to show you the
attachment that we have now where you
can download this, open it up, and you
can see that we both have the PDF of the
sales shipment as well as the electronic
document. So jumping back to business
central
for transfers it is also uh much similar
flow as we are used to. I'll just
quickly show that if you go to locations
you can now on any given location go
under warehouse and then see that we
have a new field called e documents
transfer document sending profile and
this is just like you're used to sending
it up on the customer. you set it up on
this location and when you then post a
transfer order it will automatically be
picked up and sent uh based on your
configuration.
Then as a little bonus I wanted to also
uh talk about that we added uh the
ability to create electronic documents
from posted uh documents and this will
be all the document types that we
support. So, if I just create a new
invoice on this customer,
we'll just put in
reference 5. And again, just any given
line here.
And we just post this one. So, I haven't
set this uh customer up to work with
with e documents. And now I'm going to
post it. And we're going to see that
there is no e document attached to it.
So, if I go under related, I no longer
have the option of open, but I can click
create. I'm going to do that now. And
it's going to say that this document
sending profile we have is not set up to
be using electronic documents. And that
is because you need to go on the
specific customer and either change the
current document sending profile you
have to use e documents or change to to
one that is um compatible. So I have one
here that's called e document sales. I
can just select that or you could modify
the existing one. We can go back and now
we can just click create and that will
just run the workflow in the background
exported and for this specific document
sending profile I am connected to a
integration. So in this one it's bearero
so this has been sent to bearero and now
we are actually waiting for them to
process that invoice and check that
everything is okay and that's why the
the status of the document is in pending
response.
And very finally, if you create a sales
invoice, I showed you before, you can
use workflow to set up uh emailing. You
can also now go under post and send. And
as as you can see, the electronic
document is picked up because that is
set on this document sending profile.
But you can now also under email select
email attachments and select e document
and PDF and e document if you want to
also send to the customer uh the
electronic document. And that is
everything what uh what is new.
>> Thank you Magnus. As as you could see we
deliver uh e shipments e transfer
shipments but even a little bit more not
only this long times require
functionality such as uh uh sending um
via email sending invoice any documents
via email or sending from uh already
posted uh elect invoice sales invoice if
you didn't set up properly earlier. So
there are a lot of small things we
improved in this release. So before we
close this session, I would like to
remind you we have a good general
business center resources on all these
links. So please go there and learn
more. Also, I would like to encourage
you to go and subscribe to our LinkedIn
profile. You can find good weekly news
announcements. And when you go to
YouTube AKMsBC YouTube, you can find
this video and other videos about
electronic documents and not only
documents, all other uh videos related
to this edition and for previous
editions as well. So thank you for
watching this video.